Guide to the Henry Stauffer Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Stauffer Papers
1874-1948
RG 125
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(2 boxes)
Sermons, writings, and scrapbooks document Stauffer's work as a Congregational minister. Henry Stauffer (1858-1949) was a graduate of the Yale Divinity School who served Congregational churches in Ohio, Wisconsin, and California, and was active in promoting social reforms.
Stauffer, Henry, 1858-1949
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Norma Stauffer.
Biographical / Historical
1858 Jan 29 Born in Canton, Ohio
1882-1885 Attended Otterbein University
1885 Jul 5 Ordained as United Brethren minister, Denver
1889 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1889-1895 Served under Washington Gladden as assistant minister of First Congregational Church, Columbus, Ohio; became first minister of Mayflower Congregational Church, formerly a mission chapel of Gladden's church.
1895-1903 Minister: First Congregational Church, Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio
1903-1909 Minister: Hanover Street Congregational Church, Milwaukee, Wisconsin
1909-1914 Minister: First Congregational Church, Menasha, Wisconsin
1914-1916 Superintendent: - Fox River Efficiency League
1916-1918 Superintendent - Industrial League, Wisconsin Anti-Saloon League
1918-1922 Minister: Park Congregational Church, Los Angeles, California
1922-1927 Minister: First Congregational Church, Petaluma, California
1927 Moved to Berkeley, California, joined First Congregational Church; served church in Antioch, California; had interim pastorates and speaking engagements throughout Bay area. Was instrumental in organization of South Berkeley Community Church, first integrated church in Berkeley.
1949 October Died
Scope and Contents
This collection provides documentation of a Yale Divinity School graduate who served Congregational churches in Ohio, Wisconsin and California and was active in promoting social reforms. Stauffer was an associate of Washington Gladden in Columbus, Ohio from 1889 to 1895 and was active in the 1895 "Great Awakening" in Columbus, an evangelistic campaign led by the Rev. B. Fay Mills. Stauffer's sermons, his numerous contributions to local newspapers, and other printed material in this collection reflect his concern with the relation of Christianity to social problems, especially labor issues and alcohol.
The four scrapbooks of Series I contain correspondence, newspaper clippings, newspaper transcriptions of sermons and other published writings of Stauffer, and other printed material. Series II contains a sampling of 24 sermons, all but one in manuscript form, as well as other representative writings by Stauffer.
The following items received with the Stauffer Papers have been transferred Record Group No. 53, Yale Divinity School Memorabilias at the Yale Divinity Library: Rules of the Divinity School of Yale University (n.d.); Yale Divinity School Annual Circular, 1889; Yale Theological School '89 (class poem). A hymnbook received with the collection A Collection of Spiritual Hymns ... for the Use of the Brethren in Christ, known as "River Brethren", 1876, has been cataloged. An unpublished manuscript by Stauffer, "Those Queer Mennonites", was deposited by his daughter, Norma Stauffer, in the Bancroft Library of the University of California.
Arrangement
I. Scrapbooks, 1883-1930
II. Sermons and Writings, 1889-1948, n.d.
III. Biographical Documentation, 1874-1938, n.d.
Congregationalists; Sermons, American; Clergy; Stauffer, Henry, 1858-1949
- Scrapbooks, 1883-1930; Series I
  - Volume I, 1883-1899 (Box 1)
  - Volume II, 1899-1908 (Box 1)
  - Volume III, 1909-1916 (Box 1)
  - Volume IV, 1916-1930 (Box 1)
- Sermons and Writings, 1889-1948, n.d.; Series II
  - Sermons, 1900-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2-7)
  - "A Thesis on the Teaching of Jesus Concerning his Person, According to Mark", 1889(?) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Our Heritage" (written for Stauffer family reunion), 1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Truth and Duty - A Manual of Christian Teaching", 1909 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Present Crisis in the Christian Movement", 1928(?) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter to YDS Class of '89, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The Call of the Ideal" (verse), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The New Note in the Anti-Alcohol Movement", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "What Should Germany's Punishment Be?", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "The German Contribution to American Progress", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Our Venerable Ancestors" (written for Stauffer reunion), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "How to Make Democracy Work", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Autobiographical notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Biographical Documentation, 1874-1938, n.d.; Series III
  - Including letter from Washington Gladden inviting Stauffer to become his assistant and a bound volume edited by Stauffer entitled, "The Great Awakening in Columbus, Ohio under the Labors of Rev. B. Fay Mills", 1895, with an introduction by Washington Gladden., 1883-1895 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Including clippings, material re. churches served by Stauffer, 1902-1938, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Eight photographic portraits of Stauffer, ca. 1874-1914 (Box 2, Folder 13)